[
  {
    "question": "2 Reduced Instruction Set Computers (RISC) is a type of processor.\n\nIdentify four features of a RISC processor.",
    "answer": "2 Any four from\n Uses simple instructions\n Uses fixed length instructions\n Makes extensive use of registers/ more registers\n Single cycle instructions\n Often uses pipelining\n Harwired // dedicated control unit\n Uses few addressing modes\n Makes use of caching\n Uses a small instruction set\n Often uses branch prediction\n Often uses load/store architecture\n Makes extensive use of RAM\n\n4"
  },
  {
    "question": "11 Reduced Instruction Set Computers (RISC) and Complex Instruction Set Computers (CISC) are two types of processor.\n\n(a) State two features of RISC processors.",
    "answer": "11(a) One mark per mark point\nMax 2 marks from:\nRISC processors\nuses simple instructions\nuses fixed length instructions\ninstructions only require one clock cycle\nmakes extensive use of registers/ more registers\nmakes use of pipelining\n293\n\n2"
  },
  {
    "question": "11 Reduced Instruction Set Computers (RISC) and Complex Instruction Set Computers (CISC) are two types of processor.\n\n(b) Outline the process of interrupt handling as it could be applied to a RISC or CISC processor.",
    "answer": "11(b) One mark per mark point (max 4 marks)\nInterrupt handling\nwhen an interrupt happens current instructions are completed first\nPC and register contents are saved to stack\ninterrupt vector is used to branch to interrupt service routine using the interrupt ID\ninterrupts are disabled\ninterrupt is serviced\nregister contents and PC contents are restored from the stack\ninterrupts are enabled and execution continues\n4"
  },
  {
    "question": "11 Reduced Instruction Set Computers (RISC) and Complex Instruction Set Computers (CISC) are two types of processor.\n\n(c) Explain how pipelining affects interrupt handling for RISC processors.",
    "answer": "11(c) One mark per mark point (max 4 marks)\nEffect of pipelining on interrupt handling\nmultiple instructions are active/running in the pipeline\nan interrupt could occur at different stages of the pipeline\nmakes interrupt handling more difficult\nall instructions in the pipeline have to complete\nbefore the interrupt is processed\nOR\nall instructions are saved and loaded from the stack\nin order to complete the interrupt\n\n4"
  },
  {
    "question": "4 RISC and CISC processors are used in different computing systems.\n\n(a) Describe what is meant by RISC and CISC processors.",
    "answer": "4(a) RISC max 2 any two from:\n Uses simple instructions\n Uses fixed length instructions\n Instructions only require one clock cycle\n Uses many registers\n Makes use of pipelining\n Hardwired CU\n\nCISC max 2 any two from:\n Uses many instruction formats\n Uses variable length instructions\n Makes use of different addressing modes\n Uses few registers\n Has a large instruction set\n Requires complex circuits\n Frequently uses cache\n Instructions (converted to sub-instructions that) may require many clock cycles\n Programmable CU\n\n4"
  },
  {
    "question": "4 RISC and CISC processors are used in different computing systems.\n\n(b) Identify two differences between RISC and CISC processors.",
    "answer": "4(b) One mark for each difference max 2 from:\n RISC has fewer instructions // CISC has more instructions\n RISC has many registers // CISC has few registers\n RISC’s instructions are simpler // CISC’s instructions are more complex\n RISC has a few instruction formats / CISC has many instruction formats\n RISC usually uses single-cycle instructions // CISC uses multi-cycle instructions\n RISC uses fixed-length instructions // CISC uses variable-length instructions\n RISC has better pipelineability // CISC has poorer pipelineability\n RISC requires less complex circuits // CISC requires more complex circuits\n RISC has fewer addressing modes // CISC has more addressing modes\n RISC makes more use of RAM // CISC makes more use of cache / less use of RAM\n RISC has a hard-wired control unit // CISC has a programmable control unit\n RISC only uses load and store instructions to address memory // CISC has many types of instructions to address memory\n\n2"
  },
  {
    "question": "6 A virtual machine is used to emulate a new computer system.\n\nDescribe two benefits and one limitation of using a virtual machine for emulation.",
    "answer": "6 Two marks each benefit description max 4\n\nNew system can be tried on different virtual hardware (1)\nwithout need to purchase the hardware (1)\n\nEasier to recover if software emulating the new computer causes system crash (1) as VM provides protection to other software (1)\n\nEmulate programs for the new computer system that are not compatible with the host computer / operating system (1) by using the guest operating system on the old computer (1)\n\nMore than one new computer system can be emulated (1) this allows multiple operating systems to coexist on a single computer (1)\n\nTwo marks each limitation description max 2 from:\n\nVirtual machines may not be able to emulate the new hardware (1) because this hardware may have been developed since the virtual machine was developed (1)\n\nUsing virtual machine means execution of extra code // A virtual machine might not be as efficient // resources e.g. memory or processor time are shared (1) processing time increased // performance degrades (1)\n\nUse of a virtual machine increases the maintenance overheads (1) because both host system and the virtual machine must be maintained (1)\n\n6"
  },
  {
    "question": "4 RISC and CISC processors are used in different computing systems.\n\n(a) Describe what is meant by RISC and CISC processors.",
    "answer": "4(a) RISC max 2 any two from:\n Uses simple instructions\n Uses fixed length instructions\n Instructions only require one clock cycle\n Uses many registers\n Makes use of pipelining\n Hardwired CU\n\nCISC max 2 any two from:\n Uses many instruction formats\n Uses variable length instructions\n Makes use of different addressing modes\n Uses few registers\n Has a large instruction set\n Requires complex circuits\n Frequently uses cache\n Instructions (converted to sub-instructions that) may require many clock cycles\n Programmable CU\n\n4"
  },
  {
    "question": "4 RISC and CISC processors are used in different computing systems.\n\n(b) Identify two differences between RISC and CISC processors.",
    "answer": "4(b) One mark for each difference max 2 from:\n RISC has fewer instructions // CISC has more instructions\n RISC has many registers // CISC has few registers\n RISC’s instructions are simpler // CISC’s instructions are more complex\n RISC has a few instruction formats / CISC has many instruction formats\n RISC usually uses single-cycle instructions // CISC uses multi-cycle instructions\n RISC uses fixed-length instructions // CISC uses variable-length instructions\n RISC has better pipelineability // CISC has poorer pipelineability\n RISC requires less complex circuits // CISC requires more complex circuits\n RISC has fewer addressing modes // CISC has more addressing modes\n RISC makes more use of RAM // CISC makes more use of cache / less use of RAM\n RISC has a hard-wired control unit // CISC has a programmable control unit\n RISC only uses load and store instructions to address memory // CISC has many types of instructions to address memory\n\n2"
  },
  {
    "question": "6 A virtual machine is used to emulate a new computer system.\n\nDescribe two benefits and one limitation of using a virtual machine for emulation.",
    "answer": "6 Two marks each benefit description max 4\n\nNew system can be tried on different virtual hardware (1)\nwithout need to purchase the hardware (1)\n\nEasier to recover if software emulating the new computer causes system crash (1) as VM provides protection to other software (1)\n\nEmulate programs for the new computer system that are not compatible with the host computer / operating system (1) by using the guest operating system on the old computer (1)\n\nMore than one new computer system can be emulated (1) this allows multiple operating systems to coexist on a single computer (1)\n\nTwo marks each limitation description max 2 from:\n\nVirtual machines may not be able to emulate the new hardware (1) because this hardware may have been developed since the virtual machine was developed (1)\n\nUsing virtual machine means execution of extra code // A virtual machine might not be as efficient // resources e.g. memory or processor time are shared (1) processing time increased // performance degrades (1)\n\nUse of a virtual machine increases the maintenance overheads (1) because both host system and the virtual machine must be maintained (1)\n\n6"
  },
  {
    "question": "5 Virtual machines are used in many different situations.\n\nDescribe what is meant by a virtual machine.\nInclude in your answer two benefits and two drawbacks of using a virtual machine.",
    "answer": "5 One mark for each description (Max 2)\n\n The emulation of a computer system / hardware and/or software\n … using a host computer system.\n Using guest operating system(s) for emulation.\n\nOne mark for each correct benefit (Max 2)\n\n Multiple guest operating systems / VMs can be used on the same computer.\n Different instruction set architectures can be emulated on a single computer.\n A virtual machine can crash without affecting the host machine.\n There are security benefits // Trying a piece of suspicious software and if it is / has a virus, it will only infect the virtual machine.\n Cost savings due to not needing to purchase extra hardware.\n Can run legacy applications that are currently incompatible.\n\nOne mark for each correct drawback (Max 2)\n\n A virtual machine is less efficient / has poorer performance than real machines because of extra load on the host computer\n Performance of the guest system cannot be adequately measured.\n A virtual machine may be affected by any weaknesses of the host machine.\n Costly and/or complex to maintain / implement / manage.\n Cannot emulate some hardware.\n\n6"
  }
]
